<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>aperture. on </title>
    <link>https://1rvinn.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in aperture. on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://1rvinn.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>let yourself die</title>
      <link>https://1rvinn.github.io/crude/let-yourself-die/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://1rvinn.github.io/crude/let-yourself-die/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;let yourself die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for when you live you have to ply&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by societal constructs, and cry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the confirmist wry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let the sense of self die,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and no longer you’re a node in the society;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the chains are all set free;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;eternal freedom is bestowed,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and you can fly to where you want to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;attain freedom hereby,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let yourself die.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;let yourself die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for when you live you have to ply&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by societal constructs, and cry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the confirmist wry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let the sense of self die,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and no longer you’re a node in the society;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the chains are all set free;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;eternal freedom is bestowed,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and you can fly to where you want to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;attain freedom hereby,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let yourself die.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>privacy, democratization in ai</title>
      <link>https://1rvinn.github.io/eureka/fed/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://1rvinn.github.io/eureka/fed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;recently, while reading about the recent developments in the field i realised an array of issues that, in my opinion, are being overlooked in the current paradigm:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1]. monopolisation
Due to the humongous data requirement for pre-training, we see big-data companies like the &amp;lsquo;Googles&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Microsofts&amp;rsquo; of the world having an unfair competitive edge over other smaller corporations or entities in developing such models. This not only means a handful of companies have control over such a quintessential field but also implies:
[D] soft power - greater soft power over all AI-based content, which could further transcend into propagating bias through content and controlling widespread opinions about sensitive topics across the entire world.
[P] access to user data - with the advent of time, as AI becomes an indispensable part of our lives, these handful corporations will have even greater access to user data across different use cases, making them even more powerful. Not only this but these days, the most popular LLMs use consumer data for further training, while only mentioning this very subtly in their privacy policy. This makes room for a plethora of data security leaks on the cloud where this data is hosted and other data attacks such as prompt injection.
[D] by virtue of huge data and state-of-the-art compute requirements, it is only the firms with a rich history in tech and high levels of disposable income to spend, who can establish themselves in this area, making it discriminatorily hard for smaller firms to emerge in this field. This also means a geopolitical issue for 2nd and 3rd world countries being completely dependent upon the 1st world for such foundational models.
[2]. climate impact
[D] these foundational models require huge loads of compute requirements for pre-training. This means great amounts of energy requirements, so much so that companies like Microsoft have rented complete nuclear reactors to satisfy the energy hunger of their AI programmes. This move is completely counterintuitive to the sustainability efforts being done to reverse climate change.
[S] this tradeoff, considering the first set of harms [1] as well, is completely unjustified and will only lead humanity to its doom.
[3]. low Levels of Development in the essential fields of Healthcare and Finance
[P] since these models require unrestricted access to data to be trained, coupled with the issue that healthcare and financial data being highly private, we haven&amp;rsquo;t seen any major breakthroughs in these areas. AI has immense potential to change the lives of millions provided there is enough sustainable development in these fields, but the only thing that is holding us back is access to highly private data which is a justified concern given the first set of issues [1].&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;recently, while reading about the recent developments in the field i realised an array of issues that, in my opinion, are being overlooked in the current paradigm:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1]. monopolisation
Due to the humongous data requirement for pre-training, we see big-data companies like the &amp;lsquo;Googles&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;Microsofts&amp;rsquo; of the world having an unfair competitive edge over other smaller corporations or entities in developing such models. This not only means a handful of companies have control over such a quintessential field but also implies:
[D] soft power - greater soft power over all AI-based content, which could further transcend into propagating bias through content and controlling widespread opinions about sensitive topics across the entire world.
[P] access to user data - with the advent of time, as AI becomes an indispensable part of our lives, these handful corporations will have even greater access to user data across different use cases, making them even more powerful. Not only this but these days, the most popular LLMs use consumer data for further training, while only mentioning this very subtly in their privacy policy. This makes room for a plethora of data security leaks on the cloud where this data is hosted and other data attacks such as prompt injection.
[D] by virtue of huge data and state-of-the-art compute requirements, it is only the firms with a rich history in tech and high levels of disposable income to spend, who can establish themselves in this area, making it discriminatorily hard for smaller firms to emerge in this field. This also means a geopolitical issue for 2nd and 3rd world countries being completely dependent upon the 1st world for such foundational models.
[2]. climate impact
[D] these foundational models require huge loads of compute requirements for pre-training. This means great amounts of energy requirements, so much so that companies like Microsoft have rented complete nuclear reactors to satisfy the energy hunger of their AI programmes. This move is completely counterintuitive to the sustainability efforts being done to reverse climate change.
[S] this tradeoff, considering the first set of harms [1] as well, is completely unjustified and will only lead humanity to its doom.
[3]. low Levels of Development in the essential fields of Healthcare and Finance
[P] since these models require unrestricted access to data to be trained, coupled with the issue that healthcare and financial data being highly private, we haven&amp;rsquo;t seen any major breakthroughs in these areas. AI has immense potential to change the lives of millions provided there is enough sustainable development in these fields, but the only thing that is holding us back is access to highly private data which is a justified concern given the first set of issues [1].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;with all these concerns in mind, I came across this interesting framework called Federated Learning. coupled with a very interesting encryption scheme - homomorphic encryption - it can solve all the above-listed problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;federated learning:
In the current paradigm, the data travels to the model, and the model is trained. But what if the model travels to the data for training? That is, there is no transfer of data, therefore no room for data leaks, privacy issues and greater accessibility for smaller companies without data to compete with big giants.
This also needs better innovation as the race now changes to creating novel architectures rather than winning with more data.
Additionally, now there is a greater variety of data available to train these models including personal data - healthcare, financial data. This means better foundation models and more innovation in these underdeveloped areas.
Also, it means that the model is trained on individual devices, which implies that the computational and energy requirements are divided across devices, thus offloading the burden on the central server.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://1rvinn.github.io/img/build/fed1.png&#34; alt=&#34;federated learning&#34;&gt;
homomorphic encryption:
in the current paradigm, this is how data encryption looks like during LLM inference:
&lt;img src=&#34;https://1rvinn.github.io/img/build/fed2.png&#34; alt=&#34;homomorphic encryption&#34;&gt;
the inference is done on decrypted data, which leads to a loophole that can be exploited by cyber attackers. Not only this, but it can also lead to other security issues like the LLM learning about personal details and prompt injections as elaborated in [1].
homomorphic encryption prevents this by supporting calculations to be made on encrypted data itself, mitigating any data security threats.
additionally, being based upon lattice-based cryptography, it is resilient to the rise of quantum computers which pose a threat to existing encryption schemes like the RSA.
if you notice, I have segregated the above problems into three categories - [D]: Democratization of AI, [P]: Privacy, [S]: Sustainability.
these 3 issues are often always overlooked whenever there is a big innovation, but later, people realise the importance of working on these - the same happened in the case of Internet, with heavy spending on cybersecurity, sustainability and privacy being prevalent only these days.
the above two frameworks can solve all these issues, empowering even a small startup from Maharashtra in India to compete with OpenAI based out of San Francisco. I truly believe this could be a revolutionary step for democratising AI development and boosting security.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>jobs: the man who could change reality</title>
      <link>https://1rvinn.github.io/crude/jobs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://1rvinn.github.io/crude/jobs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Steve was a wizard, he would be casting spells, and I’d be seeing people get mesmerized” &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; ~ Bill Gates on Steven Paul Jobs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calling Steve Jobs an ‘innovator’, a ‘great marketing mind’, or a ‘sharp entrepreneur’ would be an understatement. Because his abilities were nothing short of superpowers — Jobs could change reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading Isaacson’s biography of Jobs and taking a deep dive into the infinite ocean of movies, shows, and articles about Apple exposed me to the genius of Mac’s godfather. One characteristic that stuck out to me was Steve’s Reality Distortion Field. Coining the term, Bud Tribble — an early employee at Apple, described Steve’s ability to bend the realities of those around him. The ability to convince others to believe almost anything, thanks to his charm, charisma, and marketing acumen. It was said he could distort his co-workers’ sense of difficulty and make them believe that whatever impossible task they had at hand was possible.
‘In his presence, reality is malleable. He can convince anyone of practically anything.’&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Steve was a wizard, he would be casting spells, and I’d be seeing people get mesmerized” &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; ~ Bill Gates on Steven Paul Jobs&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calling Steve Jobs an ‘innovator’, a ‘great marketing mind’, or a ‘sharp entrepreneur’ would be an understatement. Because his abilities were nothing short of superpowers — Jobs could change reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reading Isaacson’s biography of Jobs and taking a deep dive into the infinite ocean of movies, shows, and articles about Apple exposed me to the genius of Mac’s godfather. One characteristic that stuck out to me was Steve’s Reality Distortion Field. Coining the term, Bud Tribble — an early employee at Apple, described Steve’s ability to bend the realities of those around him. The ability to convince others to believe almost anything, thanks to his charm, charisma, and marketing acumen. It was said he could distort his co-workers’ sense of difficulty and make them believe that whatever impossible task they had at hand was possible.
‘In his presence, reality is malleable. He can convince anyone of practically anything.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jobs undoubtedly was a great visionary, envisioning products way ahead of time — be it the Mac, iPod or iPhone. Yet, his greatest skill lay in convincing people that his vision was not just a predictive idea but a true reflection of the future. His enchanting keynote sessions, also referred to as Stevenotes, are a testament to this. Be it convincing millions to pay $900 extra for the first Mac because ‘app windows must have rounded corners’ or convincing that headphone jacks are unnecessary, he could bend others’ realities to align with his vision. Now, this is aura!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>the metamorphosis</title>
      <link>https://1rvinn.github.io/crude/the-metamorphosis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://1rvinn.github.io/crude/the-metamorphosis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Metamorphosis by Franz Kafka is a beautiful short story depicting the intricacies of human psyche and relationships. The story starts off with Gregor, the family&amp;rsquo;s sole breadwinner, waking up to find himself metamorphosed into a mammoth of an insect. Following that, Kafka describes the paradigm shift in the demeanour of those around him — his boss, his family, and even Gregor himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this pathetic condition of his, Gregor never thinks of himself. Instead, his mind is flooded with the fear of getting late for the train he has to catch, failing which he’d surely get a reprimand from his boss. This portrays how blinded humankind nowadays is, running a rat race, trying to satisfy the unsatisfiable — their never-ending greed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;p&gt;The Metamorphosis by Franz Kafka is a beautiful short story depicting the intricacies of human psyche and relationships. The story starts off with Gregor, the family&amp;rsquo;s sole breadwinner, waking up to find himself metamorphosed into a mammoth of an insect. Following that, Kafka describes the paradigm shift in the demeanour of those around him — his boss, his family, and even Gregor himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this pathetic condition of his, Gregor never thinks of himself. Instead, his mind is flooded with the fear of getting late for the train he has to catch, failing which he’d surely get a reprimand from his boss. This portrays how blinded humankind nowadays is, running a rat race, trying to satisfy the unsatisfiable — their never-ending greed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon realising Gregor’s handicap, the family understood that they must give up on the somewhat comfortable lives they were leading and get back to work in order to sustain themselves. His father picked up the job of a security guard; his mother took up tiny gags, and even his sister, Grete, although only seventeen, decided to go door to door working as a saleswoman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Gregor? Oh, he was not to be disturbed in his room. Owing to his pathetic condition, neither of his parents had the courage even to bear the sight of their metamorphosed son. In these circumstances, his sister took the responsibility of feeding her brother and cleaning his room. This continued for a while, but the initial warm love and compassion for her brother was eventually seen fading away. Specific incidents further catalysed this dwindling of emotions to the point that, leave alone his parents, even his sister, started perceiving Gregor as a burden. This further led to her pleading with her parents to get rid of it. And I’m right when I used ‘it’. She no longer believed that the insect could actually be her beloved brother, Gregor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Owing to the above incidents, I believe that ‘The Metamorphosis’ isn’t just a story about Gregor’s metamorphosis but also that of his sister. Kafka has just portrayed what is often seen in families these days: an elderly member falling terminally ill is taken good care of, but only to a point. Despite what they have done for their families, the latter eventually start perceiving these people as burdens — financial and mental — and end up leaving them to their own disposal. Another relevant example could be how, after the passing away of a family member, they’re kept alive in the heads of their loved ones by memories but, with the due advent of time, even those memories fade away and along fades the emotional connection one had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kafka’s works are known for bitterly painful endings, and this one was no different. One night, just after observing his sister’s metamorphosis, frail due to the injuries and infections he had picked up, malnourished due to the sheer lack of food, and mentally broken due to the torments he had been through, Gregor exhaled his final breaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with Gregor went the various aspirations he held — sending his sister to music school, no matter the expenses, settling in a good apartment with his parents. Here’s Kafka providing us with another lesson for life — certain incidents might completely derail your healthy, happy and tranquil life, leaving you no choice but to accept fate and let go of what held utmost importance to you, of what you held closest to your heart. Therefore, wait not for the right time to act, for the right time is right now.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
